[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hi all welcome to software engineering
radio this is your host kanchan shrinky
our guest today is chase koher face is
the founder and ceo of aim for hire a
technology recruitment agency that
partners with tech startups in austin
texas
chase wanted his company when he
realized that startup companies need a
different approach for sourcing and
recruiting for the competitive market
welcome chase really looking forward to
our conversation today where i would
love to explore the recruiting life
cycle from the candidate the company and
the recruiter's point of view is there
anything else you would like to add to
your bio before we get started
no that was fantastic and very excited
to have the discussion from all sides of
the recruiting life cycle with you
so in the show notes i've added a
related episode that we did on this
topic five years ago so my first
question to you is
has anything significant changed in the
recruiting life cycle in the last five
years and
why is there still a need for recruiting
firms
yes so over the course obviously the
last five years and with kind of covet
intervening and part of that i think
there's certainly a major
digitalization or utilization of
different software tools and technical
advancements around recruiting around
finding jobs around interviewing and
getting jobs i think you'd find probably
that a lot of the larger companies are
utilizing things that can save them time
save them resources so whether that be
systems that when you apply for a job it
helps filter through who might be the
best applicant for that job on linkedin
there's algorithms set up that will
actually try to match you with the right
job or the right company that might be
applicable to you based on your
background or based on certain nuances
of companies or skills that you have so
i think in the last five years like
really to summarize
the integration of of before recruiting
was very transactional is very a resume
is very a lot of phone screens and
personal interaction whereas now you
know technologies continue to kind of
advance and and find ways to to maybe
make that process more efficient
sometimes there probably are
deficiencies with software as we all
know it's not always perfect sometimes
you might get let you might not get the
interview that you think you deserve and
it might not even be your fault there
might be an algorithm that that somehow
kind of deleted you from the process but
with that said those are the
advancements that are occurring that you
know i think five years ago we would
have never really
thought about
whereas now you know we have screen
recordings we have video interviews we
have all different types of kind of
filters to use whether we're recruiting
on linkedin whether we're recruiting
through resumes on indeed or dice it's
just a lot of advancement that i think
enables a better scope for recruiters to
find talent and and hopefully for talent
to find opportunities so so overall that
that would that's kind of how i would
cover the the five-year advancement for
recruiting
with all the advancement in algorithms
why do we need recruiters
i guess i failed to answer that part so
recruiters you know the thing that any
recruiter would probably argue is that
you know with an ai platform or with an
ai software application
you know you can teach intelligence can
you teach consciousness can you teach
that human
decision making and you know i don't
know
if there's a right or wrong answer but
in my in our minds in my mind as a
recruiter there is a personal
relationship development that that is
created that does happen in this
world and that if people are looking for
a job that they
you know often want to speak with maybe
a human being versus a computerized
voice or a computer of some kind where
they're just inputting data other times
sometimes it's hard to put into words
what you do or why you feel like you
might be a great person for that role
you can't just type up a little
paragraph describing why you're the
perfect fit you'd rather be able to have
the personal relationship personal
connection mutual interest besides just
the job that you're applying for but
what recruiters bring to the table is
that they do this full-time
they spend 20 you know not 24 hours but
40 hours a week connecting with
prospective talent but also speaking
with companies that are hiring they'd
end up developing kind of a network a
spider web of connections that you know
if i'm a company and i'm looking to hire
or if i'm a recruit trying to find a job
i want to go to someone that's well
connected that can get me in front of a
hiring manager at a company that i
didn't know about but might be a great
fit for me or you know various other
reasons so i think recruiters for one
it's the network they develop but two
it's it's that they can be advantageous
to a recruit
just by helping them with their resume
helping kind of guide them through the
interview process and then at the end
which has become even more of a bigger
thing is kind of help with the
negotiation
to where you know if the recruit is
seeking a certain amount of money or a
certain salary or whatever that might be
and maybe they're afraid to to bring
that up or they don't want the
confrontation to come up with the
company they can use the recruiter kind
of as the middle person to to hopefully
navigate and get the best you know best
result so i'd say you know i could talk
for hours about how i think recruiters
are important but i think those are two
of the areas that are just going to be
hard for software to replicate but you
know we're certainly seeing more and
more of it so you know who knows
that makes clear on what recruiting
firms provide to the hiring company what
about the candidate
yes from a candidate's perspective i
think you must understand that that
recruiters are in the know i mean their
job is to be in contact with people that
are hiring all the time so i think from
a candidate perspective it's a great
resource to connect with recruiters just
to to be on their radar for potential
positions that might come up with that
said the one thing to keep in mind is
the recruiters do often get paid
if you take the job that they get them
or that they get you or they get you
positioned for so sometimes there's a
slight bias there towards they might
steer you in a direction that might be
favorable to both of you and that's just
something to keep in mind contextually
but the connections that a recruiter
would have it's certainly something i
would always suggest kind of trying to
build those relationships will give you
more opportunities and and more jobs
that maybe you weren't aware of just
from job boards or other types of things
what was the gap you observed that led
you to start your own farm
yes i
i think there's a very you know like any
industry there's this kind of cookie
cutter volume type of recruitment where
it's it's very
it isn't very personalized it's not very
customized to
to a recruiter or to a recruit or to the
company that you're recruiting on behalf
of it's kind of more of a broad brush
of we do it this way and we're going to
do it for every company we work with
so for us especially being in austin
texas which is a huge tech startup
community i just identified a way to to
be a bit more boutique a bit more
specialized and and in a market like
this where the demands so high the mass
messaging
outreach to recruits doesn't cut it
anymore for that type of talent it takes
someone that full time is investing
their time in establishing relationships
getting in front of candidates and
telling them about companies
and then on the flip side representing
those candidates when that those
candidates have four or five other
interview processes going on so it can
be a lot to juggle it's certainly a
full-time job so that that's really
where i identify just being a bit more
specialized in the way you go about
doing the recruitment cycle
let's now talk about the steps of the
recruiting life cycle
the steps of the recruiting life cycle
from a recruiter's perspective it's from
a company's perspective it is you are
looking at sourcing that's the top of
the funnel when it comes to prospecting
for candidates so sourcing can be a lot
of using linkedin job boards other types
of things to develop a pipeline of
talent and then from there there's
there's outreach there's getting a hold
of those people which can be unique and
if it's on facebook if it's on the email
it's via linkedin but doing your best to
just get in front of those people and
then from there it's usually a screening
of some kind letting them know about the
companies they represent the positions
that that recruiter might have for them
from a candidate's perspective it's a
lot of positioning yourself to be
sourced to be to kind of fall within
that recruiting life cycle of a
recruiter obviously to get seen and to
get potentially more opportunities at
looking at jobs
building the talent pool my question to
you is how do you ensure that this
school works
yes i think you got to look at where
your applicants are coming from you know
if you're a company that's hiring and
looking to diversify your pool of
candidates posting that job in different
places aside from just your website can
can ensure that you at least get a
diverse pool at least from different job
sites and kind of maybe some folks tend
to use certain job sites versus others
so i think that helps diversify your
pool but also distributing your job
amongst organizations in town amongst
kind of community groups if there's a
java group or there's a ruby on rails
group i think that it helps you as a as
a hiring manager as a company
develop
kind of a unique
different avenues of talent that can
apply to your job so to make sure you're
not missing out on certain pockets of
talent or certain communities that might
be a great fit and a great addition to
your company so i think it's visibility
but also i think it's proactively kind
of going out and finding ways to
search different groups in town
different universities that people come
from and colleges that they got
education from i think that kind of
helps you ensure that you're getting all
different types of talent to potentially
come to your company and also for female
engineers and and african-american
engineers like there's different ways to
go to those organizations go to those
user groups and make sure that they have
your information as a company they have
they're sharing your jobs to their
communities like those are different
ways you can kind of go and and try to
make sure that you're giving everyone an
opportunity to know that you're hiring
and and generate a diverse pipeline of
talent
let's not just start with the positions
that startup companies begin since
you're focused on startups so what
positions do they hire to begin with is
it the gamut of pro product development
management sre ensuring management or do
they start with some specific positions
yes i i would say you know depending on
you know obviously when a startup begins
there's a couple founders and sometimes
one of those founders might have product
skills or engineering skills but but
ultimately for tech startups it's having
someone in product and someone to lead
like the software engineering technical
part i think those are really the two
kind of boxes that must be checked to
develop an mvp type product that you can
take to market and then you can bring
sales marketing those types of things
now some companies do in reverse it's
it's it's hard to sell a product if it's
not created but i think some companies
maybe try to do that but i would i would
certainly say that the vast majority
start with product leadership and then
engineering management engineering vp
type positions
and then from there like you know sre
and devops type talent certainly becomes
integrated as one of the you know first
couple hires as that company begins to
scale and the infrastructure becomes
essential once they kind of start
onboarding big customers or a multitude
of customers
what about devops how has the move to
devops change things how have they
changed the expectation and landscape
for prod dev positions
yeah absolutely yes so so devops is
one of those things where i think a lot
of people might say
they're a devops engineer but maybe they
they gravitate bit towards back end
development or they gravitate a bit more
towards like system administration
type work i think the emergence of the
you know the devops term is always one
that that kind of just determining
exactly how much time they'll be
spending on either you know what areas
will they be working most in i know site
reliability certainly has become a major
focus and with a lot of the companies
hosting and different cloud services
it's it's micro service architectures it
just gives a greater emphasis on those
types of hires and having a
multi-faceted devops sre engineers is a
huge strength for a lot of companies if
you can find the right people so i would
say it's just it's certainly shifted
things but i think there's there's folks
that tend to have like a bit more dev
less ops or a bit more ops less dev so
that's just something that to be aware
of when you're hiring or recruiting for
that type of talent
one last question in the intersection
and then we'll start talking about
things from the viewpoint of the
candidate
the recent forced remote work due to
co-ed i suppose you've seen a lot of
changes due to that can you comment
yes i can comment for sure the remote
work is i think from a recruiting
perspective is going to be one of the
biggest questions you have to answer to
candidates for the foreseeable future so
many candidates we speak with now you
know won't even take a phone call unless
the role is fully remote for the for you
know for seeable future and that there's
a flexible
approach by that company of like they
won't ever require you to come into the
office you know in six months or a year
from now and changing that now it's
difficult for companies to make promises
that far ahead in a world that's
changing as
dramatically and quickly as ours does
but i think remote work in general is
certainly is certainly something that's
real and we need to take very seriously
in acquiring and recruiting for talent
they want flexibility candidates in
general like might be open to going to
an office but they want to hear from the
beginning that there is a flexible and
agile approach moving forward that they
won't be forced to come into the office
five days a week again i think kobe's
just caused that shift and for certain
talent pools with as much demand as
there is yeah companies have to kind of
flex around those requirements or that
leverage that candidates have
so and you know some smaller companies
it was an easy transition to be fully
remote as they're you know it's a lot
easier to manage a team of two or three
people fully remote on video calls but
if you have a team of 20 30 40 people
it's certainly if you're not set up with
the infrastructure
that's a very difficult transition and a
transition that a lot of companies i
think are still trying to
really kind of own and and finalize and
specialize the the way they do that so i
i think it actually helped a lot of
smaller companies in some ways because
they were already agile and they could
pivot quickly the bigger companies are
the ones i i think that will continue to
have to kind of tussle with that and
figure out a way to accommodate the
talent pool that wants to be remote
thanks for that chase now let's start
talking about this flow from the
viewpoint of the candidate
let's say i'm just out of school how do
i approach the job market what tools
should i be familiar with what should i
start focusing on
so fresh out of school i think it can be
it's intimidating for anyone that's
looking for their first job so i would
say
utilizing tools that give you visibility
to to perspective companies to
recruiters is a way that can generate an
inbound flow of people reaching out to
you versus you having to chase down
companies so so just out of school i
think preparing a general linkedin
profile
is always step one in my mind because so
much recruitment these days occurs on
linkedin and linkedin recruiter
so just creating a general profile that
i think either has your resume attached
to it or you kind of autofill some of
your your sections and linkedin with
what your resume would show i think just
keeping in mind that a lot of recruiters
utilize linkedin to search for talent so
you want to
to best i guess
best kind of represent yourself on your
linkedin profile with keywords maybe if
you're a software engineer you know tech
stacks certain languages that you have
experience with your salesperson maybe
just talking a bit more about some
percentages or some statistics that you
can share from your internships or
experience in college
from there i think indeed a dice some of
these job boards that you know you can
just post your resume to i think you
have to do that as well i mean you want
to have as many irons in the fire as
possible but i would always say linkedin
is is a number one for for me and then
following that submitting your your
resume to local and national job boards
it's just going to give you more
visibility to companies that are looking
to hire
does that change if i'm someone with
three or four years of experience
absolutely absolutely and what i would
suggest to that fresh out as well is is
on linkedin you can search through
alumni of your current university or
college or community college i mean
coding camp i think you can use linkedin
to search
familiarities with maybe someone that is
similar to you that's a year or two
older and you can potentially connect
with them and they might have
suggestions so that would be the end of
that last question as far as the three
to four years
out of grad school i would say network
network network
like think of people that you've studied
with that you've worked with that you
felt like-minded that you felt like you
had a similar maybe career trajectory or
you enjoyed working with with that
personality type reach out to those
people look at people you've worked with
in the past and see where they're
working now one of the easiest ways to
get positions get hired i mean the top
way of hiring for a lot of companies is
referrals so if if i work at the company
and i refer someone like they already
are starting at a higher percentage of
getting that job than someone that would
be a non-referral and maybe no one
really knows aside from them applying
for a job
so i would say network look at look at
people that you've worked with that have
been managers before and ask them about
you know the companies they're at
opportunities they're hearing about and
then secondarily again i think linkedin
indeed job boards you certainly want to
have that covered as well but i'd be a
little more proactive and using the
network you've established over the last
three or four years to
kind of find some opportunities that
might align with what you're looking for
that makes a lot of sense
it's always easier to get hired or it's
always easier to hire when you know
somebody
in the past absolutely
how many companies would i expect to
interview with typically
depending yeah if you're in product or
tech i would say
what we've seen is is a lot of probably
five companies at a time there's so much
demand for tech and product talent that
i think you'll see you could rack that
up i've seen some people interviewing
for seven or eight companies at a time
on the flip side you know for different
skill sets it might be closer to three
or four companies but either way there's
so much demand in the market that i
think you want to keep your options open
you want to to be in a position of of
power and leverage once you get to the
offer stages with the company so i i
think i don't know if i have a
suggestion per se but what we've seen is
typically anywhere from three to
seven or eight companies at a time
you're interviewing with but it becomes
a full-time job from that point because
you're conducting so many interviews
with each of those companies so you got
to be committed to the cause and also
your current job might falter very
noticeably once you start interviewing
with that many companies
and that's true because there are
multiple steps
when you interview
what are they
yes i think companies have become a bit
more queued into
to speeding up that process and trying
to accommodate a candidate but that's a
generalized statement there are some
companies that still have eight nine
interview steps i always suggest what
i've seen a lot of companies shifting to
is a
closer to a four-step process that would
include
kind of an intro call with the hr
department which would be a bit more
broad cultural type assessment they
share more about the company then you
dig into the you know call with a hiring
manager a panel interview with the
different team members on that team that
you're interviewing for and the final
stage is often
maybe an executive level who's who's
really half interviewing you and asking
you questions but really is trying to
get you bought into what they're doing
and see if you might be a good addition
to that cause that they're trying to
kind of chase so i would say four steps
is closer to what we see these days but
in the past you know the bureaucratic
companies they tend to have eight nine
ten interviews so i think understand
your your customer or your you know the
company you're interviewing with and ask
on you know early on what are those
stages how many stages are there i think
being aware of that is certainly a key
move for recruits
what should i expect from the recruiter
as you mentioned earlier referrals it's
it's better if you know you're part of a
referral that there's somebody lobbying
for you and making sure your resume is
considered
if it's not that how do you even know
that your resume is being read
yes i think that's the greatest fear
when you go up and apply to a job online
when you submit your resume is did my
did my info ever get reviewed and if it
did get reviewed did it get reviewed by
like an hr person or by a subject matter
expert or the hiring manager
i think that's a huge you know that's a
huge i guess issue and problem with the
whole
process is that as a recruit sometimes
you aren't going to get those answers i
mean actually more often than not you're
probably not going to get those answers
so i i think using a recruiter
can often help you kind of maybe get a
little more intel as to why they liked
you or didn't like your profile and
things you can do differently some these
recruiters again see this on a daily
basis so they they often can provide
some suggestions that might better
position you for the next job that comes
or the next opportunity but overall i
would say don't expect a lot of feedback
that's just kind of the market we're in
it's unfortunate but i would just do
your best to be keen on any details you
can find out when you do get a response
that says we're not interested you know
maybe digging around and trying to ask
and see if you can get any more intel as
to why
yeah it's certainly about the feedback
but it's also about making sure that you
know you are getting traction with that
company so yeah i i do appreciate that's
a challenge and that's why i asked you
about it but let's say resume is red you
get contacted
how do you know what to prepare for and
how long should you expect to prepare
yes
again i think knowing your audience like
you know if you're going to be speaking
with a recruiter than then maybe just
surface level you know reading about the
company or the opportunity that they
that you applied for i think if you're
interviewing with a hiring manager or
someone that is a subject matter expert
in a different area i think preparing
accordingly so this is how you can use
linkedin
and and search that person's name for
example if all you have is their name
and their title uh looking on linkedin
look at their linkedin page see where
they went to college see what they do if
they have any description of what their
current job is look at their career
trajectory and how they got to that
position you want to have as many
talking points as possible to avoid
those awkward silences in a first call
you know that first call is like a first
date it's like you want to be prepared
for the worst and hope for the best and
so i would say you know in that first
step
usually it's a very surface level phone
call or video call just to kind of run
through your resume and they'll ask to
kind of hear about your journey
and maybe they'll tell you a little bit
more about the company that that they're
at in the job
but i would be overly prepared for those
types of interviews so you can set
yourself apart from everyone else that's
doing the exact same thing in that first
interview step which is just walking
through their resume and that's the
extent of it
so this was the first interview it's
typically the screen and you mentioned
it could be over the phone or even our
video
and let's say you do okay and then there
is the detailed set of interviews
you did give us a hint of how many to
typically expect but can you talk a
little bit more about what tools the
candidates should be familiar with
how much time they should set aside is
it typically a whole day a couple of
days are spread over several days yes
depending on the size of the company
you're interviewing with i think that
varies things quite a bit but i would
say for that second step you're usually
looking at an hour long commitment
whether it be on the phone or video and
then that third step which tends to be
like the on-site interview if it's
virtual or if it's actually on site like
that's usually a half day or a full day
of interview engagement so
i would be prepared for what they call
the on-site interview which usually
includes interviewing with multiple
managers or multiple stakeholders in
different areas of the company and that
can often take at least half a day if
not a full day so that that's the
biggest part of the interview process
that's the most time consuming in my
opinion is usually you're looking at 30
to 45 minute kind of calls but the
on-site stage or that third interview is
often the longest
and do companies typically share who the
people interviewing would be so you can
do a little bit of the prep that you
mentioned earlier
ask them ask them ask them like they
sometimes they don't in fact maybe most
of the time they don't and that's just
because they have so many candidates in
play
they might be sending the same message
out to each recruit so i think you know
always ask
be thoughtful in how many questions you
ask be concise but i would say you know
ask
questions before you're going to invest
an hour or two hours of your time to
know who you're meeting with and if
there's any agenda or if there's any
specific topics that you should expect
to come up now you know recruit using a
recruiter sometimes the recruiter knows
those things and they can give you a
little bit of a little bit of prep on
what to expect but if you don't have a
recruiter or or that person is not as
communicative then i i would always say
just ask for as much detail as you can
and then go research the people you're
going to meet with if there's a certain
topic they want to discuss go read about
why the company is doing so well or why
it was named to the inc 5000 list like i
think research and be prepared for these
interviews is going to position you best
to get that job and make a great
impression with those people what are
the basic tools to be familiar with you
know drawing tools quarter pad like
tools
can you give some examples yes gosh yeah
there's so many different i think coding
kind of mar you know places where
sandboxes and different things that you
can actually kind of practice in or that
a company might even require you to
to conduct some type of coding challenge
within i haven't seen necessarily some
broad like everyone uses this one tool
so i would say really focus on your
github account as a software engineer
and and having that
updated as much as you can i understand
that you know some of that information
proprietary you cannot share it but i
think having a github account you know
really enables you to share that
obviously with a prospective company and
they can look through some of your code
samples and different projects that
you've done that way like if you're in a
technical interview or you're in a coder
rank test whatever it is it's a little
less pressure if you make a mistake or
two you can always point to well github
where i had time and someone wasn't
looking over my shoulder i was able to
do this type of work but the coding
challenges and tests are are difficult
and there's not really a
broad everybody uses the same ones per
se so i think
doing your best to have a github account
is a good backup plan to point to and
maybe share that kind of info with the
hiring manager either before or after
that interview
candidates typically given time to ask
questions either at the beginning or at
the end
and what kind of questions do you
suggest in general people should ask
yeah i i mean i think generally they
have the opportunity to maybe ask
questions at the end of an interview but
if your interview already ran over i
already went 15 minutes past what it was
supposed to the last thing a candidate
feels like doing is
is asking questions and holding that
hiring manager or that person from
getting back to their job so i would i
would certainly email prior to the
interview maybe a couple questions that
you'd like to discuss or ones that you'd
prefer to get answered before the end of
the interview that can kind of ensure
that the hiring manager is aware of that
those are questions you want answered
prior to moving to the next step but i
think more often than not you end up
running out of time and maybe you ask
one question or two at the end so as far
as those questions go i think you know
depending on the position maybe it's
just understanding what are the
expectations of this role what is the
asking about work-life balance can
sometimes be a red flag to companies so
i would keep that in mind now i'm not
saying that's fair but you know
companies are hiring you to do a job so
if you're asking questions about all the
things that include not working they it
might be a little bit more of a turn off
than if instead if you're asking about
what does it take to to become a lead
engineer at this company if you're a
junior or mid-level like how can i how
can i work my way into
more responsibilities i think asking
those questions or asking for examples
of someone that's moved up within the
company that's always something hiring
managers like to hear because they're
they're obviously wanting to hire a
players that are committed and wanting
to move up within the company so i think
at you know asking strategic questions
like that as well as if you have
questions about just how bonuses work or
how incentives work you know i think
those are questions i'd suggest versus
asking about the benefits and work-life
balance like go through the hr recruiter
interviews asking those questions when
it gets to a hiring manager ask them
about things that they deal with on a
daily basis what's your greatest
challenge mr hiring manager mrs hiring
manager that you're trying to accomplish
this quarter
and how is this higher going to impact
that
so that that's what i would suggest that
makes sense let's talk a little bit
about feedback we did talk about
feedback about the resume but
you know at this point the candidate has
invested time for the phone screen for
speaking with the recruiter and
potentially four hours with team members
is it fair to expect feedback
do companies provide feedback well it's
fair to expect it companies whether it i
think a lot of companies to be honest
you know there are
guidelines and what you can say and what
you can't say and what things could
could make that company liable so i
think companies have kind of gotten
scared by that and therefore
instead of providing you know actually
like constructive feedback
instead they're kind of guided to just
say thanks but no thanks or like it was
great meeting you but you're not this
isn't the greatest time which can be
super vague and obviously as a candidate
not very helpful
so i do think having you know when
you're using a recruiter sometimes they
can dig in and get you a little more
feedback into something that you might
you know want to work on or improve so
you can get that job next time
but
overall no i i don't you really can't
expect a lot of feedback which i know is
so unfortunate but unfortunately it's
kind of just just the way things work
with how the speed and demand and
everything that's going on companies
tend to just be so distracted by that
that they don't take the time to provide
a feedback and unfortunately it burns
that bridge right i mean you do an
interview you spend five hours your time
with a certain company and you don't get
the job you're never going to want to
interview that company again and you
might have been a great fit you were
just maybe a year or two to junior or
we're missing a certain tool of
experience so
so i think just being cognizant that
you're probably not going to get a lot
of feedback so just continuing to ask
for that you know make yourself as
transparent as possible with the hiring
manager with the recruiter of i just
love feedback to to make myself a better
potential candidate so that's that would
be my suggestion but unfortunately no i
would say you probably shouldn't expect
a lot of feedback aside from yes or no
or maybe if you were still interested
after a few months do companies allow
that like do they come you know is there
a time frame that you can reapply or be
reconsidered
yes i think usually on their job you
know usually on their job board or where
you're applying you know we'll instruct
you know have you applied to this job
before have you applied to this company
before
i would say
depending on how big that company is
continuing to apply to them an interview
even a week or two from the time you
interviewed
i mean i think that's acceptable if it's
a big company and there's different
departments it's a smaller company once
you've interviewed you're probably gonna
be waiting
you're probably gonna be waiting at
least three to six months before you
reapply to a job they have or something
like that because you've already met
their stakeholders they decided to pass
they're gonna keep your resume on file
so if they have a job that comes up that
fits you they'll reach out but from that
point with a smaller company
you kind of want to lay off the gas a
bit on on your applying to jobs and
trying to interview there again
let's switch gears and now look at it
from the viewpoint of the company
and the startup in this more
specifically so you know just to begin
how does the startup compete with
the big three or the big four but amazon
google facebook
yes it's it's a trillion dollar question
i think because big tech and amazon
google face you know the fang companies
have they set the tone in a lot of ways
of what someone should be paid what kind
of benefits they should get but they
also have the most resources so they can
offer those things so how how do you
compete with that as a smaller company
when you can't offer
three trillion dollar base salaries or
giant stock option plans
so you know speed
and and telling a story is a big part of
attracting a certain talent to win over
that now the bureaucracy of a google
amazon you're going to likely be
interviewing for a month if not longer
because there's so many different
stakeholders so as a smaller company but
you know i always say
be as efficient and as as relatively
quick as possible you want to build
momentum with that canada you want to
tell them your story you want them to
buy into what you're trying to achieve
and that it's you against you know your
company against the big tech like do you
want to go join the big tech and get a
lot of money and you're just going to be
a cog in the wheel or would you like to
be a part of something that's trying to
disrupt or trying to improve or trying
to change things so i think that telling
that story building that that mission
but also
limiting your interview process make it
as efficient as possible for the
candidate
so that they aren't interviewing with
you and then you don't talk to them for
a week or two like you want to build on
that momentum
those are ways you can compete with the
big tech the other way is offering stock
options and offering equity in the
company
that's obviously one way that you can
get candidates to you know see that hey
if if we end up getting bought or we end
up ipoing at some point you can make a
lot of money
it's a big if but it's it's a
possibility and then the third step is
just career mobility our career
trajectory career upward mobility
if you're a product manager or software
engineer you know it might be nice to
work at google for a couple years but
after a year or two you might want more
responsibility you might want to be
coding things that are are going to have
more eyes are going to be a little
outside outside of just the little
microcosm little app that you've been
working on for two years as one of
thousands of software engineers at
google you can go to a smaller company
and you're running the show you're
making decisions on how that product is
going to look how it's going to function
new technologies you can use to to maybe
make it more effective so that's the
other kind of part of i would say
competing is
sharing with a candidate if these things
are of interest to you you'd have the
opportunity at our company to do that so
i'd say those are probably the three
areas that you gotta you have to
capitalize on as a smaller company if
you want to compete how do companies
estimate the time investment for higher
because that certainly is important with
all the work that's going on at startups
yes
how do they estimate i think
in the job market we're in right now it
can take if you're hiring for a software
developer five years experience let's
say it's gonna take
anywhere from one to three months if not
longer to hire to fill that position
so a lot of our company a lot of
companies that are that are startups you
gotta you gotta be ahead of the curve as
far as posting that job getting that job
out to people in your network to share
it with their networks
starting to interview candidates but if
you start interviewing and you find
someone that you really like you've got
to move fast
and as a candidate like you you want to
be as accommodating as possible but if
it's an opportunity you really
like and you care about then then
looking at how can you make yourself
most available around that company to
meet with all the different people that
need to speak with you but i i would say
it's very hard to put a timeline on it
because the demand is so high that
it often takes at least a month if not
three or four months to fill a software
engineering or product position
earlier you had mentioned the you know
the first thing that recruiter does
obviously is building the talent pool
and screening resumes is a key part of
that
is ai used more and more in that area
a hundred percent
ai is probably the most disruptive
not just in tech but recruiting is
certainly just seeing more and more of
how you can utilize
ai machine learning to better
prospect find candidates or vet them out
you know the only fear for me and i'm
biased because i i work at a smaller
boutique type recruiting firm but is you
can create intelligence in an
application you know it's hard or maybe
impossible to create the consciousness
so understand you know looking reading
between the lines of a resume and seeing
maybe that they put themselves through
college and that they've worked three
jobs through college to get there you
know i think those are some of the
intangibles that sometimes you miss if i
don't have java all over my resume i
might miss out if that algorithm is
calculating you know a minimum of
mentioning java for five times on my
resume for example it doesn't mean i'm
not as good of a java developer as the
rest of the candidates that applied but
that's something to be aware of so i
think ai
certainly will continue to disrupt
recruiting in different ways but as a
candidate you're looking at those key
words because you know a lot of ais is
is taking into account those types of
things are key words different
experiences that you list on your resume
or your application so i wouldn't overdo
it it's a fine line between having java
on your resume 300 times versus having
it on there three times
so i would say the best thing you can do
is just continue to to be efficient in
how you write your resume how you write
your linkedin page but certainly
mentioning what tech stacks you work in
at each job
that you've been at don't list
a hundred technologies try to be
relatively concise on the areas that you
feel most like are your greatest
strengths
besides that what are the other tools
that the recruiter would use
yes they would use they're going to use
a lot of linkedin recruiter they might
even be able to use github as a way to
find talent sometimes there's local job
boards in austin texas there's a thing
called built in austin
i think they have built in chicago and a
bunch of other cities where they have
job boards that you can apply to
so i think those are tools that
recruiters are using
to identify reach out and engage with
talent so you just want to you know if
you're a candidate looking for a role
you just want to make yourself as
visible as
possible you initially talked about the
recruiters building a relationship with
candidates
what about the recruiter's relationship
with the hiring manager
yes that one is there is no like
concrete universal answer you know as
you speak to recruiters you'll start to
get a feel for which one of them have a
really good relationship directly with
the hiring manager and which one of them
might be new or might be like kind of
still figuring things out and may not
have that type of long-standing
relationship with that company i would
say again if you can look on linkedin
and look at that recruiter's background
you can kind of get a feel for like wow
they've been recruiting for 10 years or
they've been recruiting for this one
company for a long time like they
probably have very good relationships
where if it's someone newer you want to
be a little more skept cognizant
skeptical of what they can do for you
but that doesn't you know in some ways
the the newer less experienced recruiter
might have more tenacity and getting
your info reviewed getting you feedback
so i don't think there's a right or
wrong answer but the recruiters that's a
constant struggle of theirs
is to get
feedback get on the same page as the
hiring manager and vice versa because
the hiring manager knows that recruiter
can't code in java or
or do any microservice architecture but
they're the top of the funnel when it
comes to recruiting so the hiring
manager invests time with that recruiter
it's going to help both sides but
sometimes there's an ana like there's
not a great relationship there which can
just create it's just makes it a very
ineffective overall process or
inefficient
how many positions can one recruiter
work on at the same time and still be
effective
yes i would say three to five positions
would be ideal
and now if you're doing technical
recruiting so you're just looking for
software engineers then then maybe
someone can cover front end you know
three front end rolls three back and
rolls three devops rolls because they're
you know obviously they're running
searches for software engineers that
might lean front end might lean back in
by lean infrastructure so i think for a
technical recruiter they can often cover
three to five efficiently if if it's all
different skill sets it's probably gonna
be closer to three or four
so that would be you know my instruction
to companies that have recruiters is if
you really want to get the most out of
them and you have to in this market to
get tech you get engineering talent you
can't be trying to cover 20 different
roles and just doing a bad you know an
average job at all 20. you want to focus
on three where you can do an incredible
job give an incredible kind of candidate
experience and get them through you know
the interview process and be on top of
feedback and all that kind of stuff
talking about doing a great job at that
it starts with a job posting
do people invest time in writing a good
job posting
yeah
i don't know if there's a perfect way to
write them you'll probably see some if
you're if you ever search for a job of
we're looking for this unicorn that has
every experience ever and there's others
that are very dull and and kind of
straight to the point i think i always
suggest that you know you read some
articles
just by googling if you're a company
google you know some of the best job
descriptions some of the most effective
job descriptions on
a job postings on linkedin i mean
linkedin provides articles on like you
should use this kind of format to post
your job indeed also does the same thing
so if you're posting your job i think
you know do a little bit of research on
what do candidates want to hear but also
thinking about the skill set you're
hiring for if you're hiring for a
software engineer you're probably going
to want to talk in that job description
early about fully remote work or what
are the selling points you know things
that you know are major pain points for
that talent pool so that that's what i
would say is always before you write a
job description you don't have to be the
best writer of all time you can usually
take a bunch of different job
descriptions you find online and kind of
bunch them into your own but i would
take a second research you know what
makes a great job description i could
talk about it for an hour which is why i
suggest you go read about it because
there are a lot of articles on how to do
that so we talked about the interview
loop bunch earlier so i won't go back to
that once it's designed
how to make sure that the interviewers
understand it how to train them on
executing the interview loop so that
it's a pleasant experience yes
at training your your interviewers on
how to
how to not be
repeatable across the entire product i
think that's that either comes from the
hiring manager
and the ex you know the executives of
the company or it comes from hr
you know we're not going to run five
interviews just to ask the same five
questions so i think when you're
prepping your interviewers you're
training your interviewers you're
letting them know that you know we need
you know we really we need to hire for
this position here's the reason why and
then here are the questions you know
here are some questions i'd like you to
ask but also you know what what are
things you think you could ask in a
market like this when you're getting
when you're an interviewer you kind of
have to have your sales hat on every
once in a while and share with that
candidate why
why it's an attractive workplace
like you know why they should join you
versus the 50 other companies that are
reaching out to them so i think you know
when you're training your interviewers
it's important for them to understand
contextually why you're hiring because
if they don't agree that you should be
hiring they're not going to give a good
interview in fact they might scare away
candidates so helping them understand
why you're hiring things that are most
important ask for those interviewers
input because they know firsthand and
then and then having a feedback loop set
up to where that interviewer is going to
get
you know the hr person the feedback
within two hours having that structure
in place is critical if you want to
acquire high-end demand talent because
the feedback loop has to be fast if it
takes two weeks to get the next
interview set up you've lost that
candidate so i think training them on
speed and efficiency is always the most
critical part of training an interviewer
and making sure that you understand the
impact it's going to have to everything
else the interviewer is doing to to be
able to be proactive and quick about the
whole process 100 100 and transparency
like candidates like to they don't want
to hear five people telling them what
they think they want to hear if you're
one of the interviewers you can be like
hey this part really sucks about this
job or like we're having a really hard
time on back end development but that's
one of the reasons we're hiring for this
role so we're hoping you could be that
person like i think being transparent
with your interviewers on on why you
know what you really need out of the
position i think that's really important
and again just making sure that not
everybody's asking the same
question that that's like the most
common thing i feel like is then the
candidates like do these people even
communicate with each other on like what
my feedback was i'm just answering the
same question over and over like they
don't sound like they have their stuff
together i don't want to work there so
you want to look professional it's your
in a lot of ways it's your demo it's
your demonstration of your company so
you want to have a good showing even if
the candidate doesn't decide to move
forward
so interview is done people get together
to evaluate
there's two two levels of evaluation one
is fit and then there is the level
how easy is that
especially the level
level is difficult which is why you see
like these coding tests of like you know
their coding tests they graded in this
scale so we're going to say that they're
in this level i think i don't know if
that's fair and and you might lose
candidates you will lose candidates
because of that because they might have
rushed that coding test or coding exam
or maybe they had five others that they
were doing so they you know they only
did half of it that's why looking at a
github account if you can get it from a
candidate like that that can usually be
a better display
so i would say level is so difficult to
evaluate and there are tools you can use
but it just adds to the interview steps
and then that's not going to help you
get talent because you're trying to be
efficient and only do a couple steps so
i think we find a lot of companies will
will bring in you know folks that were
part of the technical interview and
really
kind of
not just evaluate the coding challenge
or not just evaluating their answers but
looking at their background companies
they've worked for
what's the level of technical bar that
they've worked at do references look at
their github account before you make the
decision of they're a staff level
engineer or they're not a staff level
engineer
so it's not it shouldn't be just about
the interview it's just about other
things that go with it exactly exactly
obviously this will play into the offer
as well so what role does a recruiter
have in designing the offer
the recruiter
does not often get to really design the
offer now they can
more often than not the recruiter is
going to be the one that relays the
offer from the hiring manager to the
recruit
so
they might have some flex like the
hiring manager might tell the recruiter
hey we want to offer them 110k but we're
willing to flex this much like see if
you can get them to verbally accept so
the recruiter is the in between that's
trying to figure out how much the
recruit wants how much the hiring
manager is willing to spend and making a
happy medium between the two but i don't
think the recruiter often has a lot of
say in how that
that is crafted they really will just
provide context to the hiring manager of
this is this is the comp range the
hourly rate they were seeking they say
that they're currently at 100k like it's
up to you mr mrs hiring manager to
decide what you want to offer
thank you chase so
i want to talk a little bit about
recruiting events now okay how are they
different and how effective are they
recruiting events are
as i'm sure anyone that's listening it's
been to one or hundreds they are
a dime a dozen in a lot of cases there's
a lot of them they're not always the
best audience or not always what you
want or hoping for but you know that
kind of just comes with the territory of
when you're trying to get
people together in a group i think there
isn't a perfect way to run an event but
i do think you know there is some
credibility if a certain organization is
running the event or if a certain
speaker will be engaging there with with
people i i think paying attention to
that and trying to see who else is going
to that event if you can you know
sometimes on
online you can see who's attending the
event and that can be a good way to
determine if it's worth your time to go
but that yeah events are difficult to
determine what is best because it might
end up being all recruiters it might end
up being all technical people and no
recruiters so it's just you never know
sometimes and that's why i suggest just
do your research before you go invest
the time
what about senior positions you know
what are the key differences when you're
either hiring for a senior position or
interviewing for senior positions
yes for a senior role i think you would
like you know as a recruit as a
interviewee you would like to
to display
multi-faceted a multi-faceted skill set
and or a very specific skill set i think
you want to tailor that around what the
job is because if a job is a you know
adobe is specifically creating docker
containers and aws like you want to be
very specific about what you can do
but most i think senior level engineers
you know want to have a little more
flexibility and creativity to work on
some things so
from there i think just describing in
your interview the process that you have
worn different hats you've tackled
different challenges tell the stories
about what the challenge was
you know what you know some one of the
interview questions asked is what's your
the greatest challenge you've overcome
i think talking about those examples of
when you stepped up as a senior engineer
as a lead engineer and how you went
about doing that is always a great
demonstration of kind of you know how a
hiring manager judges a senior member of
the team now if you're interviewing
hiring for that position it can be just
as difficult because just because
someone has 20 years experience does not
mean they're a better engineer
than the person that's five years
experience
so i think you really want you know
sometimes for a senior role you end up
having to interview maybe a couple more
times or the interviewee might ask a
couple more questions because it's just
such an important position and a hard
one to
to really nail down prior to making an
offer
winding down now
my question to you is
how do you think things are going to
change let's say after a decade
what will be the change to the
recruiting life cycle well hopefully i'm
still around as a recruiter hopefully
recruiters are still around but i think
a lot you know obviously so much has
been digitalized
to where you know a job board will will
look at your resume you know the ai will
look at your resume and start
determining what job
postings might be the best ones for you
or what companies might be the best ones
for you
so and i think that's really cool i
think there are things that it might
miss but overall i would say you know 10
years or from now i'd imagine a lot of
this is digitalized and hopefully some
of it is is rewarding the candidate i
mean i feel like in so many cases the
client the company that it does the
interviewing
has so much leverage and and or not just
has the leverage but i guess they they
can ask you and do as many interviews as
they want you know hopefully it gets to
the point where they're you know they're
not they're compensating recruits but
that they're getting the chance to give
the recruits the same options to
interview them
so i'm hoping that's
that's something in the future because
it always depends on the job market but
10 years from now it wouldn't surprise
me if a lot of this is all
recordings and digitalized and there's
no personal interaction and
that's my fear but i think that might
end up being
more and more of the case is you
recording
yourself answering certain questions and
then submitting that to the hiring
manager instead of actually talking to
the hiring manager i think that's that's
certainly where a lot of things have
progressed to to be more efficient and
using ai to evaluate your answers and
then determine if the hiring manager
should actually
look at your info that brings you the
question
what are you excited about in this whole
life cycle like as a recruiter what is
it that you love and what is it that
keeps you up at night
i think i love that i i'm not a software
engineer i'm not a you know i i can do a
little code here and there but i'm no
software engineer but i get to talk
every day to to some of the best
engineers and and data engineers
technical talent in the in the world in
my opinion so i think as a recruiter
it's so cool to get
to be able to speak with people that
maybe you normally wouldn't work with
every day
and technology is clearly the future and
best doing your best to understand that
and position your recruits to to be
happy
and get a job that checks the boxes of
what they want whether it be money
whether it be a more balanced lifestyle
whether it be they have to pay tuition
for their kids to go to college so they
need a 20k bump and pay like how can i
as a recruiter help facilitate that
in between the two so i would say that's
the most exciting part i have is just
continuing to get to work with
a talent pool and you know tech and
product that's changing the world and
maybe more drastically than any
talent pool ever has so i think that's
that's really what keeps me excited is
is the constant changes and disruption
that occurs in tech it can be scary
sometimes but overall it's just
incredible to be a part of it and get to
help in any way that i can with people
that are so smart and influential in
what the world looks like you know i
think my greatest fear you know the
thing that keeps me up at night is
certainly
you know that i think that supply and
demand of talent and being able to
continue to to find people and get them
connected to the right types of jobs i
think there's just so there's so many
there's like in this market that it's so
wild to
to try to get someone through an
interview process
because they have 10 other companies
reaching out to them
you know how do i get a hold of them how
do i make a good enough impression with
that recruit that they want to work with
me that they'll let me know if they take
another offer a lot of ghosting occurs
in recruiting where from both sides
where the recruiter might ghost the
candidate after they fail an interview
or the recruit might ghost them once
they get another offer and so it's just
it's hard to feel confident in in every
step
so that's my i would say that's what
keeps me up at night is not you know
getting those relationships built and
trust and transparency
anything we missed that you would like
to cover
i don't think so this has been
outstanding i think there's
one topic we discussed offline was just
the you know the great resignation a lot
of folks because of covid you know
during kovitz such a major part was
job security and ensuring that you had
benefits and things like that to cover
yourself and your family and
and now you know we're seeing four
million you know four million people in
july resigned 4.5 resigned in august
and and most of this is occurring in the
tech and healthcare industry
so you know in tech it's definitely the
demand and even in healthcare there's
enough tech into in healthcare now that
you know the demand is growing so
substantially
in industries that normally maybe
wouldn't even have dealt with technology
very much like healthcare you know so i
think it's an exciting time for tech and
i'm just i think with all this all these
resignations going on there's a lot of
people taking new jobs it's just
something to be aware of that there's a
lot of you know if you're an app if
you're a recruiting a recruit
there are a lot of recruits out there
right now but there are also a lot of
jobs so i think it's it's just a wild
time to be in the recruiting you know to
be looking for a job or trying to hire
right now
but a lot of opportunity how can people
how can people contact you
yes you know linkedin if i haven't said
that enough i swear linkedin should be
paying me for my endorsements of them
but linkedin chase coacher your co-her
is how i pronounce it but you can say
coach here it's k-o-c-h-e-r
if you want to look me up there or at
aimforhire.com
those are both good ways to get in touch
with me and then my email is chase aim
for hired.com so it's pretty
straightforward we'll put that in the
show notes as well it was so great
having you on today chase thank you so
much for being here with us thank you
thanks all for listening this is kanchan
shrinky for software engineering radio
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening